Guide to the Records and Papers of Terry Sanford, 1945-1998 UA.03.60.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Records and Papers of Terry Sanford
1945-1998
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sanford, Terry
UA.03.60.0001
265.5 Linear Feet
Terry Sanford was a politician and President of Duke University from 1970 to 1985. He was Governor of North Carolina from 1961-1965, a United States Senator from 1986-1992, and campaigned for the Democratic Party nomination for President in 1972 and 1976. The Records and Papers of Terry Sanford include administrative records, personal papers, manuscripts, photographs, sound and video records, and other materials gathered by Terry Sanford during his careers as a politician and the President and President Emeritus of Duke University.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
Records of the University's Board of Trustees which have been in existence for at least fifty years are available for scholarly research with the permission of the University Archivist. Access to records which have been in existence for less than fifty years shall be granted only by special permission, in writing, from the Board of Trustees.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Portions of these materials are restricted by donor request.
Unprocessed materials are closed pending processing.
Provenance
Materials were transferred to the Archives at various times from the Office of the President of Duke University, the President's House at Duke University, Mr. and Mrs. Sanford, and members of his staff, his biographers, and his estate.
Biographical and Historical Note
James Terry Sanford was born August 20, 1917 in Laurinburg, N.C., the son of Cecil L. and Elizabeth Martin Sanford. He received the A.B. degree (1939) and the JD degree (1946) from the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. After serving in the military and FBI and while practicing law in Fayetteville, N.C., Sanford embarked on a political career. He served as North Carolina State Senator from 1953 to 1954 and as United States Senator from 1986 to 1992. In 1961 he was elected Governor of North Carolina and held the office through 1965.
In December 1969 Sanford was elected President of Duke University. He assumed the office in April 1970 and held the position through June 1985. His involvement at Duke continued as President Emeritus, from 1985 to 1998, and as Professor of Public Policy, from 1992 to 1998. Terry Sanford died on April 18, 1998 and is buried in the Crypt in the Chapel at Duke University.
Sanford married Margaret Rose Knight in 1942; they had two children, Elizabeth Knight and Terry, Jr.
Collection Overview
University administrative records, personal papers, manuscripts, photographs, printed matter, memorabilia, and other material created or received by Terry Sanford during his various careers as a lawyer, politician, and President and President Emeritus of Duke University. The bulk of material consists of records from his tenure as President, 1969-1985. A folder list for these records (Series 1). Also included are substantial records on Sanford's 1972 and 1976 campaigns for the Democratic Party nominee for President, as well as personal and political files related to his many interests and activities throughout his political career. Series 2 and Series 4 as well as portions of Series 3 are not fully processed although some content information is available in the series descriptions. [Note: Materials in this collection may use outdated terms such as "mentally retarded" to refer to people with mental disabilities.]
Separated Material
Three oversize items were removed from the Records and Papers of Terry Sanford Collection and placed in the map drawers. Please refer to the seperation sheet in the collection control file for the drawer number.
Related Materials
Terry Sanford papers, 1926-1996 and undated, (bulk 1986-1992), David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
"Terry Sanford and the New South" records, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
The Terry Sanford Papers #3531 The Terry Sanford Papers #3531, Southern Historical Collection, The Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.
MARS Number 368, Terry Sanford Governor's Papers, State Archives of North Carolina, Raleigh, NC, USA.
Campus planning -- North Carolina; Educational fund raising -- North Carolina; Education, Higher -- North Carolina -- History; North Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1951-; North Carolina -- Governors -- History -- 20th century; Universities and colleges -- North Carolina -- History -- 20th century; Politicians -- North Carolina -- History -- 20th century; Knight, Douglas M., 1921-2005; Sanford, Terry; Democratic Party (N.C.) -- History; Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Duke University. Presidents; Drew Associates
- Series 1. Duke University. President Terry Sanford Records, 1969-1985.
  Scope and Contents note
  Records of the President of the University, with bulk dates 1969 to 1985. Records from earlier administrations, in particular those of Douglas M. Knight (1963-1969), are present as well. The files consist of correspondence, memoranda, minutes, proposals, reports, clippings, reference material, speeches, and other records.
  - Subseries 1.1. Subject files, 1969-1985, 175 ln. ft. (about 150,000 items
    The Subject files document Sanford's role as President of Duke, and also his continued interest in many fields including education, politics, and the arts.
    The records of the Sanford administration record the policies and actions of the University in academic planning, athletics, campus planning and the physical growth of the university, development and alumni affairs, student life, and the University's interaction with Durham and North Carolina during the 1970s and 1980s. Among the more notable academic planning matters documented are the early years of both the Fuqua School of Business and the Institute of Policy Sciences and Public Affairs, now the Terry Sanford Institute of Public Policy. Also included is correspondence from alumni, faculty, and students against the administration's proposal in 1975 to phase out the School of Forestry and Environmental Studies. Correspondents in the area of academic planning include Joel Fleishman, Director of the Institute of Policy Sciences and Public Affairs; Thomas Keller, Dean of the Fuqua School of Business; and John C. McKinney, Dean of the Graduate School, and other officers.
    Folders pertaining to the Retrenchment measures taken in 1980-1981 that eliminated the undergraduate Department of Education and the baccalaureate program in Nursing are also part of this series. These steps were recommended to the Board of Trustees in September 1980 by then-Chancellor A. Kenneth Pye in his memorandum, Directions for Progress. The bulk of the material consists of letters and memoranda from Sanford to faculty and alumni of the departments announcing the actions and correspondence from alumni, educators, and school administrators expressing their support of or opposition to the plan.
    Continuing the fundraising efforts that began with the Fifth Decade Campaign, 1964-1970, Institutional Advancement files focus primarily on the Epoch Campaign, a three-year campaign that attempted to raise $162 million from 1973-1976. The material concerns the progress of the Epoch Campaign and other fundraising efforts, such as the Loyalty Fund, 1979-1980.
    Sanford's commitment to the arts can be seen in the files on the American Musical Theater Center, 1977-1980 and the American Dance Festival, 1977-1985. The recruitment and arrival of the Festival at Duke in 1977 began a long relationship that has continued for over 20 year.
    The records also document student life, but to a lesser extent than other topics. Issues related to student activism of the early 1970s are found within Student Unrest files. These records include clippings and a scrapbook documenting the student takeover the Allen Building in February 1969, before Sanford's presidency. Material from May 1970 largely concerns student actions on campus in response to the Kent State shootings. Letters of approval or disapproval from alumni and student parents on these and other topics are included as well. The records also document another aspect of student life that Sanford faced: the use of illegal drugs. In 1971 Sanford rejected a proposal from the Associated Students of Duke University calling for a relaxed stance by the administration on the use of drugs, particularly marijuana.
    Student conduct at athletic events is also documented. On January 17, 1984 Uncle Terry Sanford sent An Avuncular Letter to students chiding them for their inappropriate behavior during a home basketball game with the University of Maryland. The file contains the original letter, many newspaper articles detailing the behavior, letters to Sanford from concerned parents and alumni, and Sanford's response to each.
    The major change in residential life during Sanford's tenure was the 1972 merger of the Woman's College with Trinity College for Men to create the present Trinity College of Arts and Sciences. While the school had long been co-educational, the merger completed the switch to co-residency. Included are correspondence from alumni, administrators, and other institutions regarding the pros and cons of the merger. There is also some correspondence regarding the future of the Woman's College administrators.
    Sanford's interest in all levels of education is found throughout the files as well. During the 1960s and 1970s he served on the Board of Directors of the Learning Institute of North Carolina (LINC), a non-profit agency dedicated to improving education through experimentation and research. The LINC records, dating from 1965-1979, consist of correspondence, minutes, reports, and reference material.
    The records also illustrate how national and international issues played out on campus. Among these are investment policies in South Africa, in which students, faculty, and the administration began questioning Duke's support of U.S. businesses with investments in South Africa. Regarding the Panama Canal Treaty (1977-1978), Sanford attempted to put together a panel debate with Jesse Helms, Henry Kissinger, and others participating. Correspondence is included with these two, President Jimmy Carter, and others.
    Among the other major issues of the Sanford administration were the Nixon Library Controversy, 1981-1982, (3.5 boxes). These files concern the debate over whether Duke should house Richard Nixon's presidential library. Sanford argued in favor of the library as a valuable archival repository. Letters of support and disapproval from faculty, alumni, and other sources in and out of the University community are included. Correspondence dates from as early as 1971.
    In 1981 Duke co-sponsored and Sanford a this public series of speeches and debates by a bipartisan group of political leaders concerned with reforming the process of nominating presidential candidates (Duke University Forum on Presidential Nominations). Co-sponsored by the Woodrow Wilson International Center, the first event was held on 11 May 1981 in Washington, D.C. Speakers and panelists included Robert Dole, Gerald Ford, Vernon E. Jordan, and Robert Strauss.
    Soviet-American Track Meet files consist of correspondence, minutes of meetings, committee lists, schedules, and planning for the twelfth annual event held the first week in July 1974. Sanford's continued interests in politics are documented in files on the Democratic Party, 1970-1982. Correspondents include Senators John Glenn and Ted Kennedy. Sanford assisted in founding the Education Commission of the States in 1965/66. Headquartered in Denver, Col., the Commission provides research and advice to assist states and school systems in long-range planning and decision-making.
    As Governor, Sanford was instrumental in the founding and early years of the North Carolina School of the Arts in Winston-Salem, N.C. Included is correspondence related to the Sanford Scholarships, a program begun in 1975 awarding four full-tuition scholarships named in his honor. Sanford also served on the Advisory Board of the State Zoo Authority in the early 1970s during the planning of the North Carolina Zoological Park (Asheboro). The files include correspondence regarding proposed site locations.
    Among Sanford's correspondents were Walter Cronkite, Doris Duke, James E. Holshouser, Hubert H. Humphrey, James B. Hunt, James G. Martin III, George McGovern, Richard Nixon, and Robert W. Scott
    Arrangement note
    Arrangement: alphabetical
    - A. General correspondence, 1970-1985 (Box 1)
    - Abortions (Box 1)
    - Academic Council (Box 1)
    - Academic Council. Consultative Session (Box 1)
    - Action (Joseph Blatchford), 1971-73 (Box 1)
    - Adams, Anne, Dr. - see Duke Reading Center (Box 1)
    - Adams, James L. (Box 1)
    - Administration Review, 1984 - see Kaludis, George (Box 1)
    - Administration, 1969-1972 (Box 1)
    - Admissions Office (Box 1)
    - Admissions, 1971 [subdivided into schools and colleges, special cases, etc.] R ESTRICTED (FERPA) (Box 1)
    - Admissions, 1971-1974 RESTRICTED (FERPA) (Box 2)
    - Admissions, 1975-1977 RESTRICTED (FERPA) (Box 3)
    - Admissions, 1977-1979 RESTRICTED (FERPA) (Box 4)
    - Admissions, 1980-1981 RESTRICTED (FERPA) (Box 5)
    - Admissions, 1982-1983 RESTRICTED (FERPA) (Box 6)
    - Admissions, 1984-1986 RESTRICTED (FERPA) (Box 7)
    - Adolescent Services, Inc., 1971 (Box 7)
    - Advocates Program (Box 7)
    - Africa - see Pan-Africa Track Meet, 1971 (Box 7)
    - African Society, 1977 (Box 7)
    - Afro-American Society (Box 7)
    - Agency for International Development (Dept. of State) (Box 7)
    - Alaska (Box 7)
    - Alaska Pacific University (Box 7)
    - Albright, S. Allen (Box 7)
    - Alcoholic Beverages, 1970- (Box 7)
    - Alcoholism Research Council (Box 7)
    - Allen, George V. and Mrs. George V. (Kitty) - Chair, etc. (Box 7)
    - Allied Arts of Durham (Box 7)
    - Alumni Affairs, 1970-1973 - Roger Marshall (Box 7)
    - Alumni Affairs, 1977-1981 - Paul Vick (Box 7)
    - Alumni Affairs, 1982-1985 - Laney Funderburk (Box 7)
    - Alumni Affairs, Loyalty Fund (Box 8)
    - Alumni Complaints (Box 8)
    - Alumni Distinguished Alumni Awards (Box 8)
    - Alumni Letters (Box 8)
    - Alumni Letters. Class of 1973 (Box 8)
    - Alumni Magazine (Box 8)
    - Alumni Meetings, Alabama - Georgia (Box 8)
    - Alumni Meetings, Boston, Chicago, Cleveland (Box 8)
    - Alumni Meetings, Connecticut, Detroit, Pittsburgh (Box 8)
    - Alumni Meetings, Denver, Nashville, Norfolk, Tulsa (Box 8)
    - Alumni Meetings, Florida (Box 8)
    - Alumni Meetings, General (Box 8)
    - Alumni Meetings, London, England (Box 8)
    - Alumni Meetings, New York (Box 8)
    - Alumni Meetings, North Carolina (Box 8)
    - Alumni Meetings, Texas (Box 8)
    - Alumni Meetings, West Coast (Box 8)
    - Alumni Meetings. Interns Reception, Washington, D.C. (Box 8)
    - Alumni National Council (Box 8)
    - Alumni Replies. Class of 1982 (Box 8)
    - Alumni Scholar Program (Box 8)
    - Alumni Weekends, 1981-1985 (Box 8)
    - American Academic Youth Exchange (Box 9)
    - American Arbitration Association (Box 9)
    - American Arts Alliance, 1978 (Box 9)
    - American Arts Alliance, 1979 (Box 9)
    - American Arts Alliance, 1980-1981 (Box 9)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (Bill Bevan) (Box 9)
    - American Association of Presidents of Independent Colleges and Universities (Box 9)
    - American Association of University Administrators (Box 9)
    - American Association of University Professors (Box 9)
    - American Association of University Students (Box 9)
    - American Association of University Women (Box 9)
    - American Bar Association (Box 9)
    - American Bar Association. Special Commission on Coordination of Judicial Improvements (Box 9)
    - American Cancer Society, 1970-1980 (Box 9)
    - American City Corporation (Box 9)
    - American Committee on East-West Accord (Box 9)
    - American Committee on U.S.-Soviet Relations (Box 9)
    - American Council of Learned Societies, 1971-1972 (Box 9)
    - American Council of Learned Societies, 1973-1975 (Box 9)
    - American Council of Young Political Leaders, 1976-1985 (Box 10)
    - American Council on Education, 1970-1973 (Box 10)
    - American Council on Education, 1974-1985 (5f) (Box 11)
    - American Dance Festival, 1977-1985 (10f) (Box 11)
    - American Federation of Labor - Congress of Industrial Organizations (Box 11)
    - American Institute for Public Service, 1981-1985 + n.d. (Box 11)
    - American Institute of Certified Public Accountants, 1975 (Box 11)
    - American Legion (Box 11)
    - American Musical Theater (Box 12)
    - American Musical Theater (Box 13)
    - American Psychological Association (Box 14)
    - American Quadricentennial Corporation (Box 14)
    - American Red Cross (Box 14)
    - Americans for the Coast (Box 14)
    - Amos, John (Box 14)
    - Andrews, Ike (Box 14)
    - Anlyan, Fritz (Box 14)
    - Anlyan, William G., Dr., 1970-(3f) (Box 14)
    - Anniversary, 50th, 1974 (Box 14)
    - Appalachian Community Service Network, 1980-1981 (Box 14)
    - Appalachian Community Service Network, 1981-1986 (Box 15)
    - Appalachian State University (Box 16)
    - Applicants for Jobs, 1970-1984 (Box 16)
    - Architect, 1980-1984 (Ward) (Box 16)
    - Architect, 1970-1980 (Younts. Ward) (Box 16)
    - Archives, University (Box 16)
    - Armour, George. 1972. Scotland property (Box 16)
    - Army Research Office, Durham, NC (Box 16)
    - Art Affairs (Box 16)
    - Art Center - Art Museum, 1965-1969 (Box 16)
    - Art Center - Art Museum, 1970-1983 (Box 17)
    - Art. White Collection (Col.&Mrs. V.R.) (Box 17)
    - Arts Ascending, Ltd. (Box 17)
    - Arts Associated Councils of the Arts (Box 17)
    - Arts Councils of America (Box 17)
    - Arts Education Conference, 1979 February 9-10 (Box 17)
    - Arts and Sciences Capital Campaign (Box 17)
    - Arts, National Endowment for the (Box 17)
    - Ashmore, Frank (Box 17)
    - Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies (Box 17)
    - Associated Universities, Inc., 1970 (Box 17)
    - Association of American Colleges, 1970-1975 (Box 17)
    - Association of American Colleges, 1976-1979 (Box 17)
    - Association of American Colleges. Presidential Search, 1977 (Box 17)
    - Association of American Universities, 1969-1974 (Box 17)
    - Association of American Universities, 1975-1982, 14 folders (Box 18)
    - Association of American Universities, 1983-1984, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Association of American Universities. Bartlett, Tom. Review (Box 19)
    - Association of American Universities. Council on Federal Regulations (Box 19)
    - Association of American Universities. Graduate Education Program (Box 19)
    - Association of American Universities. Industrial Research (Box 19)
    - Association of American Universities. Meetings, 1970- (Box 19)
    - Association of Governing Boards (Box 19)
    - Athletic Council, 1971-1985, 8 folders (Box 20)
    - Athletic Policy, 1981-1985, 3 folders (Box 20)
    - Athletic Policy. NCAA Rules (Box 20)
    - Athletics, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Athletics. Association for Intercollegiate Athletics for Women, 1982 (Box 20)
    - Athletics. Atlantic Coast Conference (Box 20)
    - Athletics. Basketball Coach, 1970-1977 (Box 21)
    - Athletics. Basketball Coach, 1978-1982 (Box 21)
    - Athletics. Basketball Coach, 1983-1985 (Box 21)
    - Athletics. Butters, Tom, 1977-1985 (Box 21)
    - Athletics. Cameron, Eddie M., 1970-1972 (Box 21)
    - Athletics. College Football Association (Box 21)
    - Athletics. Concerned Iron Dukes Association (Box 21)
    - Athletics. Conduct at Games (Box 21)
    - Athletics. DUAA (Box 21)
    - Athletics. Football Invitations, 1970-1977, 8 folders (Box 21)
    - Athletics. Football Invitations, 1978-1984, 7 folders (Box 22)
    - Athletics. Intercollegiate Athletic Council (Box 22)
    - Athletics. International Track Meet, 1974 (Box 22)
    - Athletics. James, Carl, 1972-1977 (Box 22)
    - Athletics. McGee, Mike, 1970-1978 (Box 22)
    - Athletics. Sloan, Steve (Box 22)
    - Athletics. Soccer (Box 22)
    - Athletics. Swimming (Box 22)
    - Athletics. Wilson, Red. Termination, 1982, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Atlantic Council (Box 22)
    - Atomic Energy Commission, 1971-1974 (Box 22)
    - Awards, 1971-1985, 7 folders (Box 22)
    - Awards. Charles A. Dukes Awards (Box 22)
    - Awards. Trinity Award, Trinity Medal (Box 22)
    - B. General correspondence, 1970-1985 (Box 23)
    - Baker, Lenox D. (Box 23)
    - Ball, Edward (duPont) (Box 23)
    - Banks - miscellaneous (Box 23)
    - Banner, Leslie (Box 23)
    - Barchas Center for the History of Science and Medicine (Box 23)
    - Barristers Club (Box 23)
    - Bassett, John Spencer (Box 23)
    - Beatty, Croom V (Box 23)
    - Belk Family (Box 23)
    - Benenson, Edward H. - Awards - Gifts of Books, etc. (Box 24)
    - Berea College (Box 24)
    - Bevan, William A. (Box 24)
    - Bicycle paths (Box 24)
    - Bioethics Conference (Box 24)
    - Black Affairs, President's Council on (Box 24)
    - Black affairs (Box 24)
    - Blake, Pamela Jane (Ladd) (Box 24)
    - Blaydon, Colin (Box 24)
    - Blue Devil (Box 24)
    - Blue Devil Club (Box 24)
    - Board of Visitors, Business Administration, School of (Box 24)
    - Board of Visitors, Engineering, 1969-[1983] (Box 24)
    - Board of Visitors, Forestry, 1979-1983 (Box 24)
    - Board of Visitors, Fuqua, 1977-1984 (Box 24)
    - Board of Visitors, Fuqua, [Information books, 1983] (Box 24)
    - Board of Visitors, Institute of Policy Sciences and Public Affairs, [1981-1983] (Box 24)
    - Board of Visitors, Law School, 1973-1983 (Box 24)
    - Board of Visitors, Medical Center, [1971-1976] (Box 25)
    - Board of Visitors, Woman's College (Box 25)
    - Boesky, Ivan F. (Box 25)
    - Books Exposure Program (Council for Public Schools, Inc.) [1970-1971] (Box 25)
    - Borchardt, Professor Frank. Computerization of Language Oriented Enterprises (Box 25)
    - Boy Scouts of America (Box 25)
    - Boyd, Alan S., 1972. Management Executives' Society (Box 25)
    - British-American Festival, 1984 (Box 25)
    - Brookside Miners (Duke Power&United Mine Workers, 1973-1974) (Box 25)
    - Brown Memorandum, 1983. Alumni responses to confidential memo of advice and commentary (Box 25)
    - Brown Memorandum, 1984. Alumni responses to confidential memo of advice and commentary (Box 25)
    - Bryan, Joseph M. 1976-1978 (Box 25)
    - Bryan, Joseph M., Bryan University Center, 1979-1984 (Box 25)
    - Bryson, Edwin C. (Box 25)
    - Bubas, Vic. 1966-1977 (2f) (Box 25)
    - Buettner-Janusch, Prof. John (Primate facility) [1970-1972] (Box 25)
    - Buildings at Duke (Box 25)
    - Buildings, dedication of [1970-1984] (Box 25)
    - Buildings. Bryan University Center Dedication [1981-1983] (Box 25)
    - Buildings. Jones Cancer Research Building, dedication of, 24 Sept. 1976 (Box 26)